Guide to the Albert M. Mathewson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Albert McClellan Mathewson papers
1735-1941
MS 990
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
The Albert Mathewson Papers consist of correspondence, financial, business and legal records and genealogical material of the Lanman, Trumbull and Huntington families, ancestors of Mathewson. His own personal papers (1888-1941) are largely related to his professional activities, with the Connecticut State Shellfish Commission, among others.
Mathewson, Albert McClellan, 1860-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cornelia D. and Albert M. Haskell, 1943.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Scrapbooks are available on microfilm (397 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM83.
Scope and Contents
The Albert M. Mathewson Papers consist of letters, volumes, and miscellaneous papers of Albert M. Mathewson and his ancestors in the Lanman, Huntington, and Trumbull families.
The papers were given to Yale University Library by Cornelia D. and Albert M. Haskell in 1943.
Biographical / Historical
Albert McClellan Mathewson, LL.B. 1884.
Born October 19, 1860, in Woodstock, Conn.; Died September 20, 1943, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, William Williams Mathewson, a farmer in Woodstock; son of Rufus Smith and Faith Williams (McClellan) Mathewson of Brooklyn and Woodstock, Conn. Mother, Harriet Augusta (Warner) Mathewson; daughter of Benjamin and Sarah (Gazley) Warner of New Berlin, N.Y. Yale relatives include: Jonathan Trumbull (LL.D. 1779) (great-great-great-great-grandfather); Jonathan Trumbull (LL.D. 1797) (great-great-great-grandfather); Shubael Abbe (B.A. 1764) (great-great-great-uncle); John McClellan (B.A. 1785) (great-grandfather); Benjamin Silliman (B.A. 1796), Isaac Webb (B.A. 1822), and John McClellan (B.A. 1833) (great-uncles); Arthur Mathewson (B.A. 1858) (uncle); and Cornelius D. Haskell, '08, and Albert M. Haskell, '10 (nephews).
Woodstock Academy; taught school in Woodstock; attended Yale School of Law 1882-84 (LL.B. 1884; member Kent Club) and 1889-91 (LL.M. 1891); admitted to the bar 1884; lawyer in Putnam, Conn., 1884-88 and New Haven 1888 until retirement 1934 (in office of Judge Henry E. Pardee [B.A. 1856] 1888-89; associated with Chase [Prentice W., '87 L.], Mathewson & Chase [Prentice T., '12 S., '17 L.] 1915-25); clerk of Shell Fisheries, State of Connecticut, 1896-1905; judge New Haven city court 1905-11; author: The Graves of the Signers of the Declaration of Independence from Connecticut (1909), Model of Charter for the City of New Haven (1912), Our Mercantile Marine (1915), The County System of Connecticut (1917), and of many papers on early New England history, delivered before the new Haven Colony Historical Society; president American Loan Company 1927 and New Haven Council Boy Scouts of America; vice-president for New Haven County, Connecticut Prison Association, 1911-33; an organizer in 1921 and vice-president and general counsel Citizen's Bank and Trust Company 1921-30; secretary-treasurer Young Men's Republican Club 1926; on advisory board Bankers National Insurance Company of New York and Salvation Army (chairman 1929); member executive committee of board Beneficial Loan Society of New York; founder Boys Good Government Club 1908; trustee Junior Republic Association, Litchfield, Conn., 1919-43; on board of managers New Haven Boys Club and Friends of Boys; served on Legal Advisory Board during World War I; honorary member Corbey Court; member New Haven Grays 1889-92, New Haven Colony Historical Society (assistant secretary 1915-37, secretary 1937-39, chairman committee on relics 1929-39), Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, Society of Mayflower Descendants, Society of Descendants of Signers of the Declaration of Independence (president 1907-08 and 1924), Sons of the American Revolution (historian 1923), New Haven County Bar Association, State Bar Association of Connecticut, American Bar Association, and Center Church (Congregational), New Haven (member First Ecclesiastical Society and delegate New Haven West Association of Congregational Ministers and Churches 1924).
Married June 13, 1888, in New Haven, Mary Elizabeth Board Foster, daughter of Edmund Kingsmand and Abigail (Heard) Board. No children. Mrs. Mathewson died November 15, 1940.
Death due to carcinoma. Buried in Woodstock Hill Cemetery, Survived by a stepson, Pierrepont B. Foster, '03, three stepgrandchildren, and a sister, Mrs. Ellen Trumbull Mathewson Haskell of Wakefield, Nebr.
In 1941, Mr. Mathewson gave a collection of volumes and pamphlets to the library of the Yale School of Law.
Taken from Yale University Obituary Record, 1943-1944.
Business; Juvenile delinquency; Oyster culture; Connecticut; New Haven (Conn.) -- Politics and government; Lawyers; Public officers; Bowen, Henry Chandler, 1813-1896; Lanman, David Trumbull, 1802-1866; Lanman, Peter, 1771-1854; Mathewson, Albert McClellan, 1860-; McClellan, Mary T.; Trumbull, Joseph, 1782-1861; Waterman, Darius; Huntington family; Landman family; Trumbull family
- Inventory
  - ALS, by Joseph Trumbull to an unidentified recipient, 1735 (Box 1)
  - Draft summons, to Darius Waterman of Lebanon, Ct., 1772 (Box 1)
  - Personal and business papers, of the Lanman, Trumbull, and Huntington families, 1806-1836
    - Personal and business letters received by Peter Lanman (1771-1854), Joseph Lanman, and David T. Lanman (1802-66), from their Huntington, Trumball, and Lanman relations (Box 1)
    - Financial papers of Peter Lanman and David T. Lanman (Box 1)
    - Financial papers of Peter Lanman and David T. Lanman (cont'd) (Box 3)
    - Personal letters received by Eunice Backus (Mrs. Jonathan) Trumbull (1749-1826) (Box 1)
  - Copybook and volume of poems, of Mary T. McClellan of Boston, 1816 (Box 1)
  - Accounts, of the Lucius W. Leffingwell estate, 1850-1888 (Box 1)
  - Bankbook, of David C. Sanford, 1872-1873 (Box 1)
  - Receipt, of Henry C. Bowen to Benjamin Warner, 1876 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous papers, of Albert M. Mathewson regarding the Connecticut State Shellfish Commission, the Connecticut Oyster Growers' Association, the Woodstock City Court and other New Haven institutions, the history of the Trumbull family, and various personal matters, 1888-1941 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbooks of clippings and other papers, of Albert M. Mathewson on the Connecticut oyster industry (1883-1900), his own political career (1894-1913), and free admission of boys to Yale Bowl games (1907-25). [These volumes are available only on microfilm.], 1883-1925 (Reel 1)